Guide to the Ruth Asawa Papers M1585
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Ruth Asawa papers
1926-2014
bulk
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Asawa, Ruth
M1585
228 Linear Feet: 278 containers (206 boxes, 39 flat boxes, 22 map folders, 7 cartons, 4 card boxes, 1 tube)
The papers of sculptor Ruth Asawa relate over eighty years of her rich and varied career, with documentation concerning her art and commissions as well her involvement in arts education, civic art, and art administration.
Access to Collection
The materials are open for research use. Selected audiovisual media have been reformatted and are available for access via the Special Collections Reading Room.
Scope and Contents
The papers of Ruth Asawa relate over eighty years of her rich and varied career, with documentation concerning her art and commissions as well her involvement in arts education, civic art, and art administration. The collection includes correspondence, notes, memoranda, transcripts, exhibition notices and other publicity, articles and publications, design sketches, blueprints and plans, photographs, and audiovisual media. The majority of correspondence is incoming, with some drafts of outgoing, including some from her husband Albert Lanier, particularly in the 1950s. Asawa retained her maiden name for her art, but otherwise used Lanier.
Although the collection has been divided into broad series, there are countless intersections between the various spheres of her life. References between especially relevant series have been noted. Beyond Asawa's own art and advocacy work, her papers chronicle the mid-to-late 20th century art, design, and architecture worlds, as well as the civic and cultural life of the San Francisco Bay Area. Her work with the San Francisco Art Commission, the California Arts Council, and other organizations, as well as her close friendship with other artists such as Imogen Cunningham, are especially valuable in this regard. In addition, her personal experiences as an internee during World War II, attending Black Mountain College, and raising a large family as a working artist provide further research opportunities.
Together, the Ruth Asawa papers serve to reinforce the values she fought for: the experience of making art as creative thinking and problem solving, breaking down the false barriers between art and science, and fostering an inclusive engagement with the arts among people of all ages, but especially young people.
Biographical / Historical
Ruth Aiko Asawa Lanier (1926–2013) was a sculptor, painter, and printmaker acclaimed for her biomorphic wire forms and public art installations, as well as her activism in art education. Asawa was born in the agricultural community of Norwalk, California on January 24, 1926, to Japanese immigrant parents Umakichi and Haru. She was the fourth of seven children. Her father was a truck farmer, and the family worked in the fields to support the business. Asawa showed an aptitude for art at an early age. In 1939, she won a school art competition with her drawing of the Statue of Liberty. On Saturdays, she attended a community Japanese language and cultural school, where she practiced calligraphy. Although Asawa had hoped to attend art school in Los Angeles, World War II and the signing of Executive Order 9066 changed everything. She was sixteen years old in February 1942 when her father was arrested by FBI agents and separated from his family for the next six years. A few months later, the family received orders to relocate. Asawa's mother, who knew very little English, had to orchestrate the closing of the farm on her own. They were at the Assembly Center at Santa Anita racetrack for six months, and were later moved to a more permanent camp in Rohwer, Arkansas. Thanks in part to a sympathetic teacher, Ruth excelled in her art classes, and became the art editor of the class yearbook. She graduated from Rohwer High School in 1943, at a time when certain Nisei were permitted to leave camp to continue their studies, as long as they stayed away from the coasts.
She applied and was admitted to the Milwaukee State Teachers College on a scholarship sponsored by the National Japanese American Student Relocation Council, an initiative of the American Friends Service Committee. She studied drawing, weaving, pottery, painting, printmaking, and jewelry with Robert von Neumann, Elsa Ulbricht, Winifred Phillips, and Joseph Friebert, intending to become a schoolteacher. To support her education, Asawa found work as a domestic servant and measuring hides in a tanning factory. In the summer of 1944, a teacher and several students traveled to Black Mountain College, an experimental school in North Carolina, for a workshop series known as the Summer Institute, and returned with positive reports. Ruth considered attending the summer of 1945, but instead she and her sister Lois traveled to Mexico City to study Mexican art and history. Among her instructors was designer Clara Porset, who also told Ruth about Black Mountain College. After attending the 1946 Summer Institute, Asawa decided to continue at Black Mountain. She spent three transformative years there under the guidance and instruction of teachers such as Josef Albers and Buckminster Fuller, who became lifelong friends and mentors. She also met her husband Albert Lanier at Black Mountain College. Albert had transferred from Georgia Tech to study architecture and design. In 1947, Asawa returned to Mexico on a trip again sponsored by the Quakers, where she observed local techniques for crocheting baskets which would inspire later work in wire.
In June of 1949, Ruth traveled to San Francisco to join Albert, who had come out earlier to find a job and aplace to live. They were married a month later, and lived on Jackson Street in downtown's produce district. Ruth continued her studies by taking silkscreening, drawing and dance classes at San Francisco State College. The 1950s and 60s saw Ruth diving headlong into painting, drawing, paper folding, printing, casting, and her innovative crocheted wire forms. In addition to Albert's work as an architect and draftsman, they both began working in industrial design, creating and selling fabric patterns and other designs, as well as promoting Ruth's wire sculpture as an interior through Laverne Originals. However, they soon chose to focus on developing Ruth's career in the art world, which at the time meant New York. A series of successful and favorably reviewed shows at Manhattan's Peridot Gallery led to national exposure. Asawa has held major solo retrospective exhibits at the San Francisco Museum of Art (1973), the Fresno Art Center (1978 and 2001), the Oakland Museum (2002), the M.H. de Young Memorial Museum (2006), and the Japanese American National Museum (Los Angeles, 2007).
Aside from her wire sculptures, Asawa is perhaps best known for the many public commissions she created in the Bay Area. Her most famous public sculptures are "Andrea," the mermaid fountain at Ghirardelli Square (1966); the Hyatt on Union Square Fountain (1973); the "Buchanan Mall (Nihonmachi) Fountains" (1976); "Aurora," the origami-inspired fountain on the San Francisco waterfront (1986) and the "Japanese-American Internment Memorial Sculpture" in San Jose (1994). She also served as guest faculty at San Francisco State University, where she worked with landscape architects to create the outdoor "Garden of Remembrance" (2002).
In addition to her full-time work as an artist and activist, Ruth and her husband raised six children: Xavier, Aiko, Hudson, Adam, Addie, and Paul. In 1968 Asawa joined Sally Woodbridge and other parents to found the Alvarado Arts Workshop at Alvarado Elementary School, where her three youngest children were enrolled. With limited financial support and using cheap or recycled materials such as milk and egg cartons, leftover paint, scrap fabric, and bakers' clay, they began to bring working artists in to work with the students. Ruth formulated a teaching philosophy based on her personal experience: children develop as critical thinkers by practicing art and gardening. With the arrival of busing in San Francisco, the Alvarado program spread to other schools. This expansion was helped greatly by the 1973 federal Comprehensive Employment and Training Act (CETA) program, which provided resources for artists to teach throughout San Francisco. Building on the Alvarado model, Ruth was central to the creation of the San Francisco School of the Arts (SOTA) high school, which was renamed the Ruth Asawa San Francisco School of the Arts in 2010.
Asawa served on the San Francisco Art Commission, the California Arts Council, the National Endowment for the Arts, and on the Board of the Fine Arts Museums of San Francisco, the American Conservatory Theater, and SCRAP. She received honorary doctorates from San Francisco State University, the San Francisco Art Institute, and California College of the Arts, and in 1999 she received the Bachelor of Arts degree from the Milwaukee State Teachers College that she had been denied as a student in 1946. In 1982, February 12 was declared Ruth Asawa Day in San Francisco. Ruth Asawa died on August 5, 2013, at her home in San Francisco at age 87.
Adapted from Wakida, Patricia. "Ruth Asawa." Densho Encyclopedia.
Arrangement
Asawa's papers were organized by her family prior to their arrival at Stanford, and for the most part their arrangement was retained. Most files are chronologically ordered. Although there is considerable overlap throughout the various series, the following general categories were used: 1. Correspondence, Professional 2. Public Art Projects 3. Art Projects 4. Art 5. Correspondence, Artists and Colleagues 6. Lectures, Workshops, Classes, Events 7. Writing and Transcripts 8. Alvarado Arts Workshop and Alvarado Elementary School 9. San Francisco School of the Arts 10. Ruth Asawa Fund 11. Education and Schools, General 12. Student Art and Correspondence 13. Black Mountain College 14. Public Service 15. Activism and Advocacy 16. Fellowships and Grants 17. Awards and Honors 18. Correspondence, Personal 19. Calendars, Planners, Notebooks, etc. 20. Clipping Files, Bibliography 21. Biographies and Portfolios 22. Juvenalia, School 23. Japanese American Internment 24. Family 25. Miscellaneous Photographs and Media 26. Clippings by Asawa
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Purchased, 2007. Accession 2007-208. Gift, 2007, 2010, and 2014. Accessions 2007-336, 2010-213, and 2014-069. Gift of Addie Lanier; Accession 2017-273.
Arts in education; Japanese American artists; Artists -- California -- San Francisco; Public art; Art -- Study and teaching.; Asawa, Ruth; Asawa, Ruth
- Series 1. Correspondence, Professional, 1951-2013
  Scope and Contents
  Contains incoming and outgoing draft correspondence concerning Asawa's career as an artist, primarily with galleries, museums, agents, and patrons about exhibitions, loans and sales. The majority are chronologically arranged. Many of the files from the 1950s document the Laniers' industrial design efforts, including work for Laverne, The Englander, and others.
  - Art Cataloging by Paula Freedman, 1998-1999 (Box 100, Folder 1)
  - Art Gifts, 1961-1991 (Box 100, Folder 2)
  - Art Donations, 1980-1997 (Box 100, Folder 3)
  - Art Loans, 1965-2001 (Box 100, Folder 4)
  - Bartlett H. Hayes, Jr. to Asawa at Black Mountain College, 1948-11-29 (Box 100, Folder 5)
    Hayes was the director of the Addison Gallery of American Art, where Ruth first exhibited. The check for her first sale (to a man named Vandenberg) had been mailed to Norwalk.
  - Si [Sillman?] to Asawa, early 1950s (Box 100, Folder 6)
    Undated drawing with text: "anytime you can send the sculpture we’ll exhibit. soon maybe? love si." Probably before her Sillman and McNair Associates show in New Haven, which opened September 28, 1953.
  - Laverne Originals, Inc., 1951-1954 (Box 100, Folder 7)
  - 1951-1952 (Box 100, Folder 8)
  - textile designs (Everett Brown Associates, The Englander), 1952 (Box 100, Folder 9)
  - 1953 (Box 100, Folder 10)
  - 1954 (Box 100, Folder 11)
  - Peridot Gallery, undated (after 1954) (Box 100, Folder 12)
  - Peridot Gallery, 1953-1954 (Box 100, Folder 13)
  - 1955 (Box 100, Folder 14)
  - Peridot Gallery, 1955 (Box 100, Folder 15)
  - Peridot Gallery, 1956 (Box 101, Folder 1)
  - folded paper design, 1956 (Box 101, Folder 2)
  - 1956 (Box 101, Folder 3)
  - Peridot Gallery, 1957 (Box 101, Folder 4)
  - 1957 (Box 101, Folder 5)
  - 1958 (Box 101, Folder 6)
  - Peridot Gallery, 1958-1960 (Box 101, Folder 7)
  - 1959 (Box 101, Folder 8)
  - 1960 (Box 101, Folder 9)
  - sales, rentals, 1960-1961 (Box 101, Folder 10)
  - Peridot Gallery, 1961 (Box 101, Folder 11)
  - 1962 (Box 101, Folder 12)
  - Peridot Gallery, 1963 (Box 101, Folder 13)
  - Ankrum Gallery (Los Angeles), 1962 (Box 101, Folder 14)
  - 1962 (Box 101, Folder 15)
  - Shop One (Rochester, New York), 1962-1963 (Box 102, Folder 1)
  - 1963 (Box 102, Folder 2)
  - Estelle Dodge Associates, Inc., 1962-1963 (Box 102, Folder 3)
  - 1964 (Box 102, Folder 4)
  - Tamarind Lithography Workshop, 1965-1992 (Box 102, Folder 5)
    Related Materials
    See also Tamarind printed materials file.
  - 1965 (Box 102, Folder 6)
  - Pasadena Art Museum, 1964-1965 (Box 102, Folder 7)
  - 1966 (Box 103, Folder 1)
  - 1967 (Box 103, Folder 2)
  - 1968 (Box 103, Folder 3)
  - 1969 (Box 103, Folder 4)
  - 1970 (Box 103, Folder 5)
  - 1971 (Box 114, Folder 1)
  - 1972 (Box 114, Folder 2)
  - San Francisco Museum of Art, 1972-1973 (Box 114, Folder 3)
  - 1973 (Box 114, Folder 4)
  - Van Doren Gallery, 1973-1974 (Box 114, Folder 5)
  - 1974 (Box 114, Folder 6)
  - 1975 (Box 114, Folder 7)
  - 1976 (Box 104, Folder 1)
  - 1977 (Box 104, Folder 2)
  - 1978 (Box 104, Folder 3)
  - Santa Cruz, 1978-1979 (Box 104, Folder 4)
  - 1979 (Box 104, Folder 5)
  - 1980 (Box 104, Folder 6)
  - 1981 (Box 104, Folder 7)
  - 1982 (Box 104, Folder 8)
  - 1983 (Box 105, Folder 1)
  - 1984 (Box 105, Folder 2)
  - 1985 (Box 105, Folder 3)
  - 1986 (Box 105, Folder 4)
  - 1987 (Box 105, Folder 5)
  - 1988 (Box 105, Folder 6)
  - 1989 (Box 105, Folder 7)
  - 1990 (Box 105, Folder 8)
  - 1991 (Box 176, Folder 1)
  - Open Studio, 1116 Castro, 1991-11 (Box 176, Folder 2)
  - 1992 (Box 176, Folder 3)
  - 1993 (Box 176, Folder 4)
  - 1994 (Box 106, Folder 1)
  - J.J. Brookings Gallery, 1994-1997 (Box 106, Folders 2-5)
  - 1070 Lombard St. gate (Box 106, Folder 6)
  - 1995 (Box 106, Folder 7)
  - 1996 (Box 106, Folder 8)
  - 1997 (Box 106, Folder 9)
  - 1998 (Box 106, Folder 10)
  - 1999 (Box 106, Folder 11)
  - 2000 (Box 107, Folder 1)
  - 2001 (Box 107, Folder 2)
  - Fresno Art Museum, 1996-2001 (Box 107, Folders 3-4)
  - Fresno Show 2001 – Oakland additions, 2002 (Box 107, Folder 5)
  - Oakland Museum, 2001-2002 (Box 108, Folder 1)
  - Brooklyn Museum of Art, 2001-2002 (Box 108, Folder 2)
  - 2002 (Box 108, Folder 3)
  - 2003-2004 (Box 108, Folder 4)
  - 2005-2006 (Box 108, Folder 5)
  - 2007-2013 (Box 108, Folder 6)
- Series 2. Public Art Projects, 1964-2002; 2.
  Correspondence, memoranda, notes, photographs and administrative material related to Asawa's public art commissions. Files are in approximate chronological order by project. All works are in San Francisco, California unless otherwise noted.
  - 2.1 J.L. Hudson Company, Detroit, 1964-1965
    Asawa's first professional commission came from designer Gere Kavanaugh's interest in her work following the 1960 de Young show. Wire sculptures were placed in Joseph Magnin department stores in both San Francisco and Topanga Canyon. No files from this are present. Kavanaugh, who worked for architects Victor Gruen Associates, then arranged for Asawa to create ten tied wire sculptures for display at Westland Center, a Detroit-area shopping mall.
    - correspondence, memoranda, notes, etc. (Box 117, Folder 1)
    - photographs (Box 205, Folder 3)
  - 2.2 Fox Plaza fountain, 1964-1966
    Asawa designed a fountain and wire sculpture for the lobby of this large mixed-use building named for the theater it replaced at 1390 Market Street. Victor Gruen Associates was the architect for the project. The 1975 San Francisco Bicentennial Survey of Art Work in the City and County of San Francisco describes the fountain as follows: "Tens of hollow tubes 3-4 feet tall of anodyzed bronze come together at the base and then spread out and tip downwards as petals of a flower, allowing water to dribble out. Two other similarly composed anemone-like forms with diameters of approximately 10" and 15" rest at the bottom of the marble fountain." In the midst of a 2008 lobby remodel when the property was to be put on the market, the fountain was removed.
    - correspondence, notes, etc. (Box 117, Folder 2)
    - photographs (Box 205, Folder 4)
  - 2.3 Bethany Center mosaic, 1967-1968
    Asawa designed a colorful mosaic based on tied wire designs for the entrance to the Bethany Center Senior Apartments at 580 Capp Street. Alfonso Pardinas of Byzantine Mosaics did the fabrication. Extra tiles were used in mosaic projects at Alvarado and Edison Elementary. Bethany is now home to Ruth's Table (http://www.ruthstable.org), an arts workshop in her honor.
    See also Bethany Center printed materials file
    - correspondence, notes, printed items, etc., 1967-1968 (Box 117, Folder 3)
  - 2.4 Ghirardelli Square, "Andrea Fountain", 1965-2005
    After the Ghirardelli Chocolate Company relocated to the East Bay from its San Francisco factory in the early 1960s, there was widespread concern about the fate of the historic location, and William Matson Roth and Roth Properties intervened by purchasing the entire block for a pioneering adaptive reuse project known as Ghirardelli Square. The architectural firm of Wurster, Bernardi and Emmons was used, as well as landscape architect Lawrence Halprin.
    Prior to Ruth's involvement with the project, Albert Lanier was contracted to assist with the design. Although shops and restaurants began to move in by 1964, the Square was not formally dedicated until the Spring of 1968, when the fountain was completed.
    Overall concern about representing an appropriate historical environment without kitsch was present from start, with Halprin's modernist aesthetic a considerable factor. Asawa was known for her abstract wire sculpture, but she chose something different for Ghirardelli.
    The Andrea Fountain, featuring two mermaids cradling infants surrounded by turtles, frogs and lilly pads, was still informed by nature, but more human, whimsical, even sentimental. Ruth attributed its Italianate character and aquatic theme to the proximity of North Beach and the Wharf. It was installed at night to appear as if it had always been there.
    Friend, neighbor, and namesake Andrea Jepson was the model for the mermaids. Her body was cast for the molds, and woven wire was used for constructing their tails. Jepson was also involved with Alvarado Arts Workshop, which began around the same time.
    Halprin's disapproval of Asawa's design eventually led to his distributing a press release distancing himself from the fountain, but as can be seen in the enclosed editorials and letters of support, the public was overwhelmingly supportive. The fountain, located approximately at 900 North Point Street, has since become one of San Francisco's most recognizable icons.
    This series contains correspondence, memoranda and other material from Ruth Asawa, Albert Lanier, William Roth, Roth Properties president William Lemmon, Karl Kortum (Ghirardelli Square board member and head of the Maritime Museum), Lawrence Halprin and Associates, developers Stuart and Caree Rose, Onno de Ruyter of the S.F. Art Foundry, and others. There are also design sketches and notes, as well as many photographs and slides.
    - correspondence (Box 117, Folder 4)
    - letters of support (Box 117, Folder 5)
    - Isenberg inquiry and interview, 2005 (Box 117, Folder 6)
      Rutgers historian Alison Isenberg researched Ghirardelli and the fountain for a journal article and later a book.
    - printed items, article clippings, 1967-2004 (Box 117, Folder 7)
    - Asawa notes (Box 117, Folder 8)
    - photographs (Box 205, Folder 5)
    - slides (Box 205, Folder 6)
    - scrapbook by Warner Jepson [unfoldered] (Flat-box 238)
      Jepson was Andrea's husband at the time, and documented the fountain's creation and installation. At one point, Ruth considered playing recordings from Jepson, an electronic music composer, through speakers around the fountain.
    - original design concept drawing, four mermaids (Flat-box 78, Folder 4)
    - Ghirardelli, Ruth Asawa and Mae Lee [audio], 1997-04-04; 1 audiocassette(s) (Box 41, Folder 10)
      Lee, Asawa, other (Addie Lanier?) re: mermaid fountain at Ghirardelli Square.
  - 2.5 Grand Hyatt Hotel, "San Francisco Fountain"
    The materials consist of
    The San Francisco Fountain, like the mermaids in Ghirardelli Square, has become a cherished part of San Francisco's landscape. Located outside the Grand Hyatt Hotel at 345 Stockton Street, the fountain consists of 41 curved cast bronze panels depicting San Francisco landmarks modeled in baker's clay.
    Ed Bassett, a partner and chief designer at Skidmore, Owings and Merrill, first saw Asawa's cast dough work at a Spring 1969 exhibition and wanted her to create a fountain for Skidmore's Hyatt project using the technique. Hyatt president Donald Pritzky had some reservations, and according to a story, said "I'm afraid it will look like a big cookie," to which Ruth replied, "It will!" The contract was signed November 1970, and the fountain was dedicated two years later in October 1972.
    Building the fountain was not only a vast group effort, it was explicitly designed that way: to make participation a part of the process. 250 people aged 3 to 90 contributed to the dough designs, including 120 Alvarado School students. Asawa had three main assistants- Mae Lee, Sally Woodbridge, and Aiko Cuneo. Albert Lanier calculated the fountain’s dimensions and with Hector Villanueva constructed a wooden model in the Lanier backyard. Woodbridge contributed architectural research, and Ruth herself traveled around the city taking pictures.
    As with Ghirardelli, San Francisco Art Foundry did the casting. Ruth’s mother Haru made trees, grass, and sea gulls. Imogen Cunningham, who is featured on the fountain, did a palm tree like the one in her yard. Ruth's friends Alan Brooks, Mark Adams, and Beth Van Hoesen are also portrayed, as well the Foundry, Skidmore’s offices, even the Mermaid Fountain.
    The San Francisco Fountain was part of the Smithsonian's Save Outdoor Sculpture survey in 1992, and made headlines in 2014 when a new Apple Store expressed interest in redesigning the plaza without sufficient assurance that the fountain would remain. Of course, following public outcry, this was made clear. The fountain would only be moved a few feet.
    - correspondence, 1970-1990 (Box 118, Folder 1)
    - foundry and other payments (Box 118, Folder 2)
    - research material (Box 118, Folder 3)
    - notebook with correspondence and notes (Box 118, Folder 4)
    - photographs, printed material (Box 118, Folder 5)
    - publicity (articles and press releases) (Box 118, Folder 6)
    - oversize blueprints, drawings, etc. (Map-folder 66)
    - booklet in braille for Lighthouse for the Blind event, 1998 (Flat-box 78, Folder 2)
    - photographs
      - proposal, sample panel, etc. (Box 205, Folder 7)
      - 1116 Castro backyard and studio, Haru Asawa, etc. (Box 205, Folder 8)
      - dough panels (Box 206, Folder 1)
      - foundry (Box 205, Folder 9)
      - dedication, other images of Ruth and fountain, 1973 (Box 206, Folder 2)
      - fountain detail (Box 206, Folder 3)
      - snapshots of 1993 rededication, etc. (Box 206, Folder 4)